Ok, so we pick up on מ"א עמוד א', Mem Aleph Amud
Aleph, four lines from the top, תא שמע, Tashma, and the last
thing we have been discussing is a debate of עולא Ulla in
the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan saying that even though you
cannot make something forbidden that isn't yours against through, you know, not
through a physical reality, as I said before, you can obviously if
you cook somebody's meat and milk together you do make it into
meat and milk. But something for which הלכה Halacha status is not
purely based on a physical reality, you cannot make it forbidden if
it is not yours. And,
but even though that's true, but if you do an action to
it to take control over it, then you actually can make it
forbidden. And the example was שחיטה shechting an animal as an offering
to עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. And the position that was contrary to
that רב נחמן, רב אמרם, ורב יצחק Rav Nachman, Rav Amram, and
Rav Yitzchak that said even if you do an action you cannot
make it forbidden. Within that there was a discussion about how big
of an action, the beginning of the שחיטה shechita and so on,
but now we're going to focus on the principal debate about whether
an action to somebody else's object can make it forbidden. So let's
take a look. תא שמע, Tashma, come and hear. שנים אוחזין בסכין
Shenayim Ochezin Basakkin in our משנה, Mishna, two people holding a knife,
apparently one at each end, ושוחטין ve-shochtin and they שוחט. shecht. אחד
לשום אחד מכל אלו, Echad lishum echad mikol elu, some, one of
them is thinking, you know, I'm going to שוחט shecht this animal
as a way of an offering to the mountain, to the star,
to the moon, to whatever it is, a thought of עבודה זרה.
Avoda Zara. ואחד לשום דבר כשר, ve-echad lishum davar kasher, and the
other has a כשר kosher thing in his mind. Presumably he just
wants to eat meat, but whatever it is, not a thought that
would be a problem. שחיטתו פסולה, Shechitatu pesula, it's invalid because at
least one of them has the wrong thought. Okay, so now we
have a question.
So what's the question? The question is why is it invalid if
you can't make something forbidden that isn't yours? So why is it
invalid? Because now, how do you know it isn't his? But I
guess they're assuming that if two people are doing it, then presumably
maybe it's not owned by either of them, or maybe we can't
assume it's owned by either of them because there are two different
people involved. So here, how can the one who has the עבודה
זרה Avoda Zara thought make it forbidden if it's not necessarily owned
by him? Okay, so you see that at least with an action
you can make something forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara says הכא במאי
עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, what are we talking about? דאיכא שותפות בגווה.
de-ika shutafut begavah. No, he has partnership in it. Although they're two
people, it doesn't mean that we can't assume either own it. It
means the same way if I thought you said one person was
שוחט shechting you would assume he was the owner, when I say
two people are שוחטין shochtin you should assume that they're joint owners.
And since at least he's a partial owner, that he has enough
of owner, the fact that he has some ownership is enough for
him to affect the status and to, and to, so no, so
the, that's a good question. חידוש Chiddush is that it's not that
he doesn't have to be, that even if it's not the only
thought that defines the שחיטה, shechita, just one of the thoughts, and
even though he doesn't own the whole thing, you know, that would
be the חידוש. chiddush. Okay, that what's the simple חידוש chiddush of
the משנה Mishna that similar to
the question, you know,
you asked the
other day, right?
That was exactly the משנה, Mishna, two people שוחטין, shochtin, that you
don't have to be, right.
No, because we already had שוחט לעובד כוכבים שחיטתו כשרה ורבי יוסי
פוסל,
shochet l'oved kochavim shechitatu keshera ve-Rabbi
Yose posel, right, and now it's just saying that if it's not
you don't have to be the whole שוחט, shochet, you can even
be a partial שוחט, shochet, and according to the גמרא Gemara you
don't even have to be the whole owner, you could just be
a partial owner. Okay, but you cannot prove that that's a case
where you are not the owner. תא שמע, Tashma, come and hear.
המדמע המטמא והמנסך. Hamidameya hametamei ve-hamenasech.
So this is a very famous משנה Mishna and this is talking
about a principle called היזק שאינו ניכר. hezek she-eino nikkar.
הלכה Halacha has a strange category, or a strange definition of היזק,
hezek, המזיק. hamazik.
It's often can be frustrating learning בבא קמא Bava Kamma because what
type of an act is considered an act of damage is very
narrowly defined and you know, people can get away with murder, but
whatever, get away with a lot. First of all you have to
be the direct person to do it. You can't do it indirectly.
So if for example, you know, I open up the gate of
my I don't know, you know, of my corral and my horses
you know, go wild and then they get to your field and
then they trample your field and destroy your field, well I didn't
do it directly. I'm sorry, it's not my problem, it's only גרמא,
gramma, it's only indirect. That's one limit, that I have to directly
physically do it. Okay, the other issue is that what defines a
damage has to be something that actually creates a physical change in
the object. If it is אינו ניכר, eino nikkar, there's no visible
damage, then it is not considered to be a damage.
So I'm trying to think of what would be like a case
of.
Or make your stuff טמא. tamai.
What, well that I know, we have the cases right here. I'm
trying to think about a more sort of real world case where
you can create a damage that's not visible.
Maybe I take your meat and it becomes rancid? Is that a
real world change?
Right, but then you could smell it and see it and so
on.
So המנסך hamenasech touching your wine?
Right, right, so those are all the cases, meaning the more, the
simpler example of damage that's not visible is damage that's because of
its religious sort of status. So that's a הלכה Halacha status. So
that's what we're going to see. I was just trying to think
like if in the
if you cost someone oh,
so suffering actually is a good point, but actually when we're talking
about human injury then suffering is a category that has to be
paid for. So maybe it's not so easy to find a case
like that in you know. In sort of the secular world, הלכתית,
halakhically, you can change things' הלכתי halakhic status in a non-visible way,
and that's considered to be היזק שאינו ניכר, hezek she'eino nikar, not
visible, and you don't have to pay. Yes.
What if you frighten, really terrify animals by doing some deed? They're
not your animals. Right.
Oh,
so that's a nice example. That's a good example, meaning psychological damage.
And if it's not, first of all, there's a good question about
could you חייב chayiv for psychological suffering not accompanying physical injury, even
by humans? But you're right, take the animal case. Let's say I
go ahead, I take your animals and I, you know, put them
into these bizarre psychological experiments or whatever, or torture, but in a
way that I actually haven't physically done anything to them, but now
it's totally unable to, you know, do the plow or to run
in the horse race or whatever it was. So that's a great
example. So that would be a היזק שאינו ניכר, hezek she'eino nikar,
a non-visible damage, and according to הלכה halakha you actually, it's not
considered היזק, hezek, you don't pay. Now there are ways in which
the rabbis closed these gaps. One is they created a category called
גרמי, garmi, which literally means my גרמא, grama, so גרמא grama is
indirect, but if it's my גרמא grama I have to pay, which
is basically a way of saying that things that they felt was,
you know, direct enough, they made you pay for. Okay, and there's
whole questions how to define גרמי garmi and whether it's rabbinic or
even biblical. Fine, that's one area. In terms of the היזק שאינו
ניכר, hezek she'eino nikar, what was direct but not visible, they made
a rule which said that you have to pay for it if
you are willfully doing it. And they basically framed this as a
קנס. knas. You know, they didn't want to let you get away
and intentionally create this type of damage and get out by a
loophole. So if it was accidental that you did this not-visible damage,
okay, technically you're exempt, and there was no intention to do it,
so it's נעבעך nebach that the other guy's not going to get
compensated, but you are not trying to do anything wrong and therefore
you don't pay. But if you were trying to do it, we're
not going to let you get off the hook and we're going
to make you pay anyway. So היזק שאינו ניכר hezek she'eino nikar
biblically is not damage, but the rabbis will make you pay if
you are doing it willfully. And that's our משנה. mishna. So let's
take a look. המטמא והמדמע והמנסך. Hametamei vehamidameia vehamenasech. So you make
somebody's תרומה teruma טמא, tamei, so you're טמא tamei and you touch
it, completely not visible, but now the תרומה teruma cannot be eaten.
והמדמע, Vehamidameia, or you mix up תרומה teruma and חולין. chullin. You
mixed up two grains, so therefore חולין chullin grain costs more than
תרומה teruma grain because חולין chullin grain can be eaten by anybody,
you don't and it can be, even כהנים kohanim don't have to
be טהור. tahor. תרומה teruma grain sold for a lot less because
it could only be eaten by טהור tahor כהנים. kohanim. If you
mix the two up, then the whole thing has to be eaten
as if it's תרומה, teruma, the whole thing is worth less. Okay,
so that's the, again, not visible. והמנסך, Vehamenasech, or you took wine
and you poured it as a libation to עבודה זרה. avoda zara.
Okay, now there of course, now it makes it worthless. Right, well,
same way טמא tamei תרומה's teruma worthless. Okay, but it's not visible.
Oh no, it's true, you have to burn it, right?
Right, it is, true. טמא tamei תרומה teruma has a, no, but
you could get הנאה hana'ah as you're burning it. All right, whatever.
Anyway, so בשוגג פטור, beshogeig patur, if it's unintentional, you're exempt for
the reason I just said, it's not visible damage. במזיד חייב, bemezid
chayav, if it's willful, you are חייב chayav because you, because we
cannot let you get off scot-free if you are willfully damaging somebody's
property. Okay, so the גמרא, Gemara, so what's the problem? Problem is
that the example is, at least in the first two cases, right,
this is what I said. Making somebody's stuff forbidden that isn't yours
is not a חידוש chiddush or not a problem when the reason
it's forbidden is based on its physical reality. So if I touch
somebody's תרומה, teruma, that's just a physical reality. It's like his תרומה
teruma is טמא tamei and therefore it doesn't matter whether it's mine
or not mine or whatever. That's just a, I mean it's like
a metaphysical reality, but whatever. The point is that it is just
תרומה teruma has transferred, you know, within the natural metaphysical world, if
you,
or
it an איסור issur by doing so.
Yeah, but we're not talking about that. Or if I, is that
an oxymoron?
I know, I was,
I was being a little ironic. But it's still different than the
case I'm going to, I'm going to talk about in a minute.
Or if I mixed up תרומה teruma and חולין, chullin, that's an
easier case to see, right? Maybe it's not visible, maybe it's yours,
but there's a reality that the two grains are mixed. So there's
no question there that I can make it forbidden even though it's
not mine because I've created a certain reality, a reality of טומאה,
tumah, maybe a metaphysical one, or a reality of mixing up, but
מנסך, menasech, where I pour the wine to עבודה זרה, avoda zara,
okay, there in order to make it forbidden I have to define
it as an offering to עבודה זרה. avoda zara. And here's where
ownership matters because what right do I have to define your wine
as an offering? It's not the physical reality that I poured it.
It's the fact that the pouring defines it in a certain way,
and there we could say you can't make something forbidden that's not
yours even through an act. That's the question though. If you said
you can do it once you're doing an act controlling it, I
understand why it's a problem. But if you said that even an
act doesn't make it forbidden, why is this wine forbidden, right? The
משנה mishna assumes that it's forbidden and the question is do you
have to pay? But why is it forbidden if you cannot make
something forbidden that's not yours even through an act? That's the question.
So the גמרא Gemara says, הכא נמי דאית ליה שותפות בגוויה. hacha
nami de'is lei shutafus begavei.
Now that is a much weaker answer in this context. We're talking
that you are part owner of this property. So because you're part
owner of this property... But I don't care that I'm part owner
of this wine, I am so angry at you, you're my partner,
I'm going to make all of our wine טמא tamei or all
of our wine אסור לעבודה זרה. assur l'avodah zarah. So you're a
part owner, which is a little crazy, because you're hurting yourself in
the process, but okay, that's the scenario, and that's why you can
make it forbidden, because it is actually yours. Okay, so here we
actually had a case where it seems very clearly not yours, you
can make it forbidden even though it's not yours through an action,
but the answer for the party, for the, for the group that
says that you can never make it forbidden if it's not yours,
even with an action, makes it a special case that you're a
part owner. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara says כתנאי. kitna'ei. This
really reflects a debate of תנאים. tanna'im. What's the, what's the debate
of תנאים? tanna'im? עובד כוכבים שניסך יין oved kochavim shenisech yayin
so here is our, I think it's a משנה, Mishnah, I don't
remember if it's a משנה Mishnah or ברייתא. Braita. Anyway, if a
non-Jew pours wine של ישראל שלא בפני עבודת כוכבים, shel Yisrael shelo
bifnei avodat kochavim, and he
pours it to his god, not in the presence of the idol.
So a non-Jew takes your wine, pours it as a libation to
his, to Zeus, but not in the presence of the idol of
Zeus. Okay, so what's the story? שלא בפני עבודת כוכבים אסרו, shelo
bifnei avodat kochavim asaro, he makes it forbidden. רבי יהודה בן בתירא
ורבי יהודה בן בבא, Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira v'Rabbi Yehuda ben Baba,
these two רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudas מתירים, matirin, say it's okay. Why?
או טוב מפני שני דברים, o tov mipnei shenei devarim, for two
reasons. אחד שאין מנסכין יין אלא בפני עבודת כוכבים. echad she-ein menaschin
yayin ela bifnei avodat kochavim. One is that people do not pour
wine as offerings to their gods except in the presence of an
idol. Number one. So he didn't really pour it to his idol.
He did, that's what he said, but his idol wasn't there. He
said he was pouring, he said he was offering it to Zeus
not in front of an idol of Zeus. So their first statement
is we don't believe that he was really making an offering. He
was just lying. He was just lying, he was just trying to
give you a hard time. Exactly. Okay, they don't make offerings not
in front of their idols. ואחד, v'echad, and number two, שיכול לומר
לו, she-yachol lomar lo, you can say to him, לאו כל הימנך
שתאסר ייני לאונסי. lav kol heimenecha she-te-aser yeini l'onsi. You have no
power, you know, to make my wine forbidden against my will. It's
very nice you want to offer my wine to עבודה זרה, avodah
zarah, but it's my wine, not your wine, and you're not in
the position to לאסר. le-asor. So the first one makes no difference
then? Right, right, but the basic point is even if you disagree
with that principle, you know, there's the other reason. Now of course
that raises interesting questions according to them, why is wine of non-Jews
ever forbidden? Now if it started as wine of non-Jews, of course
we understand, but if it was wine of Jews, right, and they
touched it, why is it ever forbidden according to them? Maybe they're
always afraid that they had a little idol in their pocket. But
even so, it's my wine and not their wine, right? So anyway,
next time we learn עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, wait another six years,
we'll come back around to it. Okay, that's an interesting question according
to them, how could a non-Jew ever make a Jew's wine forbidden?
But for us, what's important is, at least biblically, not you know
whether rabbinically we extended it
and
so on, maybe that's part of the answer, but for us what's
important is that these תנאים tanna'im say a non-Jew has no power
to make a Jew's wine forbidden. אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו
ein adam oser davar she-eino shelo even if he does ניסוך, nisuch,
even if he does a libation. Okay, the other position says no,
he does make it forbidden, so you see אדם אוסר דבר שאינו
שלו adam oser davar she-eino shelo at least through an act. So
exactly this debate of can through an act you make somebody else's
thing forbidden is exactly debated here in the context of the non-Jew.
I should say by the way I was waiting for somebody to
ask, which is if you're pouring it as a libation, how are
you trying to benefit from it afterwards? You spilled it all on
the ground. So you could have poured it into a bowl. So
you could have poured it into a bowl, but רש"י Rashi in
here basically says ניסוך nisuch does not have to mean a libation
like this, it can be enough to ניסוך nisuch to just move
your hand in it and you know some parts of like you
know maybe stirring it or dropping
some droplets, lifting it and dropping some droplets, and any of that
would also constitute ניסוך, nisuch, and that's the case in which you
could want then derive benefit from it afterwards. Yes, Charles? Is a
physical act required to make wine prohibited because of a libation? Yes,
I mean you can't do a libation without a physical act. I
was thinking of the like communion wine in the Catholic Church, would
they try to keep us from ever, ever using it? Oh, you
mean like a declaration makes it a תקרובת? tikrovet? Yeah, so normally
we say you know that that's the concept of like מוקצה, muktzeh,
which means something designated for עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, that's something designated
to be worshipped, and normally that's a problem to bring as a
קרבן, korban, but not a problem for non-קרבן korban things. For non-קרבן
korban things you need an actual act of worship or if it's
an actual becoming the object of worship or an actual act of
הקרבה. hakravah. Another phrase is like אין הקדש לעבודה זרה. ein hekdesh
l'avodah zarah. So there, yes, it's a very good question. Meaning forget
the אינו שלו eino shelo question, right, just ask within the category
of תקרובת, tikrovet, an offering, you know, does that really require an
action? Which is an excellent point and the basic answer is yes.
Okay, so alright. But anyway, according to these, according to רבי יהודה
בן בבא ורבי יהודה בן בתירה, Rabbi Yehuda ben Baba v'Rabbi Yehuda
ben Beteira, so if it's not yours, then they can't prohibit. So
even if I give it to them to נסך לעבודה זרה, nesech
l'avodah zarah, they can't prohibit? No, that's, I mean if you have
permission to use it and so on, totally. Total, total, total דיני
ממונות *dinei mammonos* ownership might not be required like we saw earlier
the whole question about is a קרבן korban *korban* considered mine if
I can derive benefit from it, right? So certain issues of relationship
and control and benefit and so on can define ownership for this
purpose. It has not been precisely defined. So it’s less that it’s
not yours, it’s more that you can’t use it in that way.
Right, a lot of this has to do with the issue about
who are you to define its status? Right, that’s what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says. Who are you to define the status of my
wine? It’s my wine, keep your hands off of it. You want
me to give it as an offering to your god, that’s all
very nice. Why should...? But if I let you... But if I
let you, it’s a different story. Yes. How come the rabbis know
so much about the practice of idolatry? Oh my god, it totally
surrounded them. No, no, let me finish my question. So much so
that they know that wine will not have significance unless it’s in
the actual presence, not metaphorically in the presence of the idol? I
mean, that goes beyond... Oh, that’s an interesting question because you mean
that’s actually learning from an absence? Meaning, even if you see all
around you people bringing, doing this stuff in front of idols, right,
what does that tell you about what happens when it happens not
in front? Right, I mean, that implies a tremendous amount of knowledge
they shouldn’t have in the first place. Well, they are totally suffused
by it by their surrounding society. If I said to you, how
do you know so much about Christmas? How do you know about
all those Christmas carols? How do you know when people go and
sing those Christmas carols? How do you know about this? Right? I
mean, if you’re suffused by it in the society, you know, you
can know a lot about it. Unless they’re imposing their own ideas
on... Well, that could also be, but... Right, that’s what I’m thinking.
Right, right, so... But you don’t need, but we don’t need an
image actually, you know, you can’t have an image to bring something
as a קרבן korban, *korban*, but I mean the fact that maybe
you don’t do it outside of a temple, you know, you don’t
bring קרבן korban, *korban*, well you bring it by a במה *bamah*
when במות *bamahs* are permissible. I don’t see this as a direct
translation of a, you know, of what we know applies by us.
It might be a direct translation of what we imagine is true
by them, you know, even if not through direct knowledge. Right, so
I don’t know, I don’t know. That’s a good... okay. All right,
yes, one last question. And at least in one space the הלכה
halachah *Halakha* ignores what the Christians are doing. I mean, it may
פוסק pasken? *posken* differently, but most rabbis will say we can’t enter
a church. But in fact, for most Protestant churches, there’s absolutely no
consecration of any building. Right, so okay, so that’s a totally separate
conversation. But it is a good question always about פוסק pasken *poskening*
about the other. Meaning, how much research have we actually done to
understand it? And even if we’ve tried to research it and understand
it, are we always, you know, in a good enough position to
judge? And should we be judging by like our standards or by
their standards or whatever, those are very important questions dealing with all
these issues, which we’re going to bracket for now. So let’s go
on. Okay. All right. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, okay, רב
נחמן Rav Nachman *Rav Nachman*, רב עמרם Rav Amram *Rav Amram*, רב
יצחק *Rav Yitzchak*, and those three who say that you can, that
even through an action you cannot make something forbidden, one Jew worshipping
another Jew’s cow or offering it up. אמרי *Amri*, they would tell
to you the following: אפילו מאן דאמר אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו
*Afilu man de'amar adam oser davar she'eino shelo*, even in that משנה
mishnah. *Mishnah* where a non-Jew can make your wine forbidden, okay, הני
מילי כותי *hani mili kuti*, that’s by a non-Jew. Again, this text
should have said נכרי *nokhri*, but you know, this text is being
censored so it’s not saying such, you know, these things about non-Jews
worshipping idols and so on. Anyway, הני מילי כותי *hani mili kuti*,
that’s about a non-Jew, literally Samaritan, what?
He says הני מילי גוי *hani mili goy*. גוי *goy*.
גוי *goy*, okay, sorry. I never know whether the original was גוי
*goy* or נכרי *nokhri*, but okay, I assume that was the original.
Okay, אבל ישראל Yisrael *aval Yisrael*, but if it’s a Jew worshipping
another Jew’s cow or offering another Jew’s cow to עבודה זרה avodah
zarah *avodah zarah* or pouring another Jew’s wine, אורי קמחבשי *urei k’mahavsei*,
he’s just trying to give him a hard time, he’s just trying
to sort of do it to spite him, to make his stuff
forbidden. We don’t assume that Jews are, as a general rule, have
sincere intentions to עבודה זרה avodah zarah, *avodah zarah*. So what they’re
actually saying is the following, which is a... one minute, right, what
we’re going to get to. It’s a radical shift. They’re saying look,
until now you’ve been assuming that our position is a person can
never make somebody else’s thing forbidden even through an action. Okay, however,
we’re willing to say another variation of our position, you know, at
least according to these rabbis here that says a non-Jew can make
a Jew’s wine forbidden. We’re willing to say it’s possible that in
principle you can make somebody else’s thing forbidden through an action, but
we would still say even according to that, that when it comes
to a Jew worshipping another Jew’s cow or offering another Jew’s cow
as an offering to עבודה זרה avodah zarah. *avodah zarah*, that he
cannot make it forbidden because we won’t believe in that case that
he sincerely, you know, doing this as an act of עבודה זרה
avodah zarah *avodah zarah*. He’s just doing it in spite and to
upset the other Jew and even if he’s saying it, and therefore
given
that’s why in this case whatever your general position is, we’re going
to usurp by a Jew to a Jew we don’t believe you
and therefore you can’t... Did he say pray to Zeus in the
process? Presumably. Well, we’re going to see exceptions to that. Okay, but...
But at least we disagree in application when it's a Jew to
a Jew. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says,
תא שמע, Tashma, come let's—let's revisit the cases we just discussed: בסכין
ושחטו אחד לשום אחד מכל אלו ואחד לשום דבר כשר שחיטתו פסולה.
Besakin v'shachatu echad l'shum echad mikol elu v'echad l'shum davar kasher shechitatu
pesulah. One is doing it for עבודה זרה avodah zarah, and
one is doing it for a kosher purpose. שחיטתו פסולה, Shechitatu pesulah,
it's
invalid. Now, before we answered, how are you, you know, how come
he makes it invalid? And we said it's because you have partnership.
But now implicitly in the גמרא'ס Gemara's question is like this: one
minute, if you say even if you say even if you say
partnership, as soon as you say partnership and that's how you can
make it invalid—wait, forget that. The גמרא Gemara is saying it's like
this. You just got through telling me that when you're dealing with
two Jews and one of them is doing something לשם עבודה זרה,
leshem avodah zarah, we assume he's not sincere. So if he's really
not sincere in this case, right, so it's two Jews, why are
you making it forbidden? Right? So why should that—why should that matter?
Let you have partnership, let you not have partnership, who the heck
cares? Right? You know, how can you make it forbidden if we're
going to suppose to assume that you're never—you're not sincere? So the
גמרא—what? Gemara The part that he owns is not—he's not doing it
for spite of the other.
So you could have said that.
You could have said, oh, since I'm going to be—my thing will
be אסור assur in the process, my half, we're not going to
assume spite. But that—that—that—so, well, he wasn't being serious to begin
with and
he wouldn't be doing that anyway.
What? No, no, the point is, if I'm only doing it to
make it forbidden and not because I'm sincere, maybe I would not
be doing that—we would have to assume sincerity in this case because
why would I want to make it forbidden if I'm going to
lose out as well? That's your question, right? So yes, the גמרא
Gemara could have answered that. Okay, let's see what the גמרא Gemara
does answer. Let's see what's the answer to that.
What? Yes, someone who is profoundly wealthy and that's a very unique
case.
Yeah,
you could have a special case too, right? Where it's my—my word,
it hurts you more than it hurts me. That's an interesting point.
But anyway, that's the גמרא'ס Gemara's question. The גמרא'ס Gemara's question is,
if we generally assume lack of sincerity when it comes to Jews
doing things לעבודה זרה, l'avodah zarah, and or let me rephrase it,
we're not willing to assume sincerity enough to make somebody else's thing
forbidden. Okay, you're trying to
make somebody else's thing forbidden, we're going to have to really know
what the problem. And if it's you as a Jew and you're
telling me because you're worshipping עבודה זרה, avodah zarah. I'm going to
be very skeptical about that. So the גמרא Gemara says, so here,
even if they were partners presumably, why can you make his—the—his half
of the cow forbidden? So let's see what the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer
is. הכא במאי עסקינן, Hacha bemai askinan, what are we talking about?
בישראל מומר, b'Yisrael mumar, like Michael said. Ah, this guy is a
known עובד עבודה זרה. oved avodah zarah. This guy has converted to
the, you know, to the cult of Zeus years ago. Okay, so
there's no question that he is sincere. So if we know that
he is sincere, that's a different story. Okay, so let's take—the גמרא
Gemara continues. Okay, תא שמע, Tashma, back to our—our other case. המטמא
והמדמע והמנסך בשוגג פטור במזיד חייב. Hametameh vehamedameh vehamenasech beshogeg patur bemezid
chayav. You poured somebody's wine as a libation. If you do it
intentionally you're חייב, chayav, unintentionally you're exempt. But either way you make
it forbidden. So same point, maybe you're just doing it to spite
me. And even if it—we have a שותפות shutfus again, maybe still
you're just doing it to spite. I don't believe that you're really
sincere about your thing of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah So הכא נמי
בישראל מומר, Hacha nami b'Yisrael mumar, same story. The guy is a
known, you know, apostate. It's known that this guy is an עובד
עבודה זרה oved avodah zarah in general. So there we do assume
sincerity. Okay, אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרב לרב אשי. Amar lei
Rav Acha brei d'Rav l'Rav Ashi. So now they asked Rav Ashi
the following case. Again, trying to—if the whole issue was the question
about sincere—how sincere are you. Let's say it's not a guy with
a past history. Never before did we see him enter the temple
of Zeus. But right now he is slaughtering this to Zeus and
here's what's happened: התרו בו וקיבל עליו התראה. Hitru bo v'kibel alav
hatra'ah. You say if you slaughter that to Zeus, you're going to
be חייב מיתה, chayav misah, it's an act of עבודה זרה avodah
zarah and you're going to be put to death. And he says,
I don't care, I'm doing it anyway. So in that case, what
do we assume? Do we think he's sincere? Probably. So מאי? Mai?
So what's the story? Can he then make my cow forbidden? Well,
let's listen to the answer. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back,
התיר עצמו למיתה קאמרת? Hitir atzmo l'misah ka'amarat? What, he's opening himself
for the death penalty? אין לך מומר גדול מזה, Ein lacha mumar
gadol mizeh, you have no greater example than somebody who really is,
you know, a—given over to עבודה זרה, avodah zarah an apostate to
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. He is obviously sincere and in that case
he would make somebody else's cow forbidden. Yes. So I would assume
something else. I'd say he's obviously mentally deranged and wants to commit
suicide, but he doesn't want to kill himself.
Ah, suicide by cop, suicide by Rab.
Yes, because once he does that, the onus of suicide is no
longer on him.
Right. Well, that's a general question to issues about the death penalty
and that actually the phrase the גמרא Gemara uses here is significant
because the גמרא Gemara was, you know, pretty—it's pretty clear that the
גמרא Gemara. was very conflicted, if you would, or, you know, by
the question about where do we as human beings have the right
to take a life of another human being. And therefore, the whole
idea of התראה hatra'ah means if you tell—if you tell the guy
you are going to get this punishment and he says I know
and I don't care. The phrase the גמרא Gemara uses here, התיר
עצמו לאותו מיתה. hitir atzmo le'oso misah. He has
himself allowed given himself over to that death. So in a way
we are not forcibly taking this person's life. He himself has accepted
upon himself the death penalty. So that whole you know that's how
חז"ל Chazal sort of structure one of the ways in which התראה,
hatraah, warning and accepting the warning functions, is to explain how we
can't take somebody else's life. But you're saying the flip side is
you know what type of crazy idiot right would ever would ever
do that which is also another thing that people point out which
is maybe it's the way חז"ל Chazal get out of ever having
to actually you know give the death penalty at all because no
idiot is ever going to do that. But you know maybe in
this case not maybe you figure heck you know I'm going to
go over to the temple of Zeus these you know these Jews
here in Israel are now being occupied by the Romans I'm going
to join up with the Roman cult and whatever and I'm going
to be protected. So you know so it's not you know whether
he actually felt you know how or I have the court in
my back pocket you know and they're on the take and I
know I'm going to get out of it. I mean you could
imagine scenarios you know but you're right I mean the question is
it's hard to imagine anybody ever really would go through this process
of accepting התראה. hatraah. No but you know but the Bobby's point
is even if he believes it why is he doing it in
a way that he's giving power to the court to execute him.
And being martyred? Right. He's being martyred. Oh that could be too.
He's doing it as an act of martyrdom.
Another excellent explanation. Okay. So now so with that we wrap up
this fascinating debate about whether you can make something forbidden that isn't
yours. We have the principle that you can in general you cannot.
Can you do it through an action? The first opinion of עולא
Ulla and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רש"י Rashi whatever it is
רבינא Ravina I think whoever whoever joined in back there. Anyway that
you can and even through a small action even just through starting
the שחיטה. shechitah. And then you have this other group of אמוראים
Amoraim רב נחמן רב עמרם that says you can't presumably even through
a large action even to a full שחיטה. shechitah. But then there
are two well one exception is עיר הנידחת ir nindachas but there
are two but besides that the גמרא Gemara, also suggests the possibility
that in principle you could but when it comes to a Jew
and another Jew and worshipping עבודה זרה avodah zarah then we are
very skeptical whether you were sincerely doing it.
Okay now you know my question is how do we פוסק?
pasken I don't know. Okay.
If אדם אוסר דבר שלו adam oser davar shelo or not? I
mean what's the question?
We basically פוסק no with an action yes. We basically we basically
פוסק רב אשי'ס Rav Ashi's פסק. psak. רב אשי Rav Ashi about
was it רב אשי? Rav Ashi? No רב הונא. Rav Huna. Yes
through an action you can be אסור דבר שאינו שלו. asur davar
she'eino shelo. Okay and then and מטמא metamei and all that?
Yes through an action so you are. Yes. Okay now let's look
at the next משנה. mishnah אין שוחטין לא לתוך
ימים ולא לתוך נהרות ולא לתוך
כלים.
Ein shochtin lo letoch yamim velo letoch
neharos velo letoch kelim. Now here all of this context has been
עבודה זרה avodah zarah you might have noticed right? Where it's you
actually have intention for עבודה זרה avodah zarah. the owner is a
non-Jew he's intending for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So this last category
are things that look like עבודה זרה avodah zarah. but aren't or
look like they might have עבודה זרה avodah zarah on the mind.
So you cannot שחט shecht into an ocean apparently that was some
form of giving the blood to the god of the ocean okay
so you can't do that ולא לתוך נהרות velo letoch neharos or
into the river for same concern ולא לתוך כלים velo letoch kelim
and not in terms of vessels why because if you're שוחט shechting
into a vessel you're collecting the blood to use it in your
idolatrous worship to sprinkle it well no it's not כיסוי הדם kisuy
hadam anyway it's a בהמה behemah not a חיה. chayah. Okay well
we're oh we always assuming חיה chayah here. בהמה. Behemah. Anyway so
if you do it into a vessel we assume that you're gathering
the blood to do to use it
in some type of a sacrificial rite. Okay so those you cannot
do but these things aren't really problems anymore like could be yeah
מראית עין maris ayin definitely could change and the question is when
מראית עין maris ayin is sort of you know encapsulated not encapsulated
anyway concretized you know in a משנה mishnah does it become הלכה
halacha in the way you know and less contextual does it become
more formal? That's a good question. In general מראית עין maris ayin
does change based on time and context and all those things. Okay
but whether it may is is more a rigorous law because it's
in the משנה Mishna is a good question. Okay you can't do
any of those because there's a concern that people will think it's
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah? אבל שחט הוא לתוך עוגה של מים Aval
shachat hu letoch ugah shel mayim but you can שחט shecht into
a like a little ditch filled with water or a little cret
whatever not what do you call it like a hole whatever a
small hole filled with water why because since the blood is getting
mixed with water nobody is going to use that for עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. Okay you'd only use unfiltered you know. And there's no
שר sar of puddles. Right and there's no שר sar of puddles.
There might be a spirit of the oceans and a spirit of
the rivers there's no spirit of puddles. So you שחט shechted it
into a little puddle you're okay. All right. ובספינה Uvesfinah now if
you're on a boat right and you don't want obviously your deck
filled with blood what do you do so you and so you
might want to שחט shecht over the side of the boat but
then it's a problem because it's going into the ocean so you
do it על גבי כלים al gabei kelim you do it on
the back of vessels not in the vessel but on the back
of vessels and as רש"י Rashi says and you have them then
you have them right
tilted so that they run off into the ocean. So, A, your
deck doesn't get bloody, just your vessels, which are easier to clean.
And B, it runs straight into the ocean. Okay, but it's not
שחטed shecht into the ocean. אין שוחטין לגומא כל עיקר, ein shochtin
leguma kol ikar,
you can never שחט shecht into a, direct into a hole directly,
because obviously same type of a concern as a vessel that you'll
use it to either to collect the blood and then sprinkle or
that there might be an idolatrous ritual around the blood itself, like
when the תורה Torah says לא תאכלו על הדם, lo tochlu al
hadam, don't eat over the blood, right, it's hard, there's twenty different
explanations what that means, but it seems like it's referring to some
type of pagan practice. So the idea that you שחט shecht and
you collect the blood into a little, into a dish and maybe
you have some ritual around that blood, so don't שחט shecht directly
into a hole. Okay, so it should be a flat surface? It
should be a flat surface or a hole that has water in
it. Right. Okay, but don't שחט shecht straight into a hole, that
also looks like some type of an idolatrous practice.
אבל עושה גומא בתוך
ביתו,
aval
oseh guma betoch beito, but let's say, but what you can do
is you can make a hole in your house בשביל שיכנס הדם
לתוכה, bishvil sheyikanes hadam letocha, that the blood should collect. What does
that mean? So it means you can שחט shecht outside of the
hole, but what happens? You don't want your floors being filled with
blood, whether it's your yard or what you're doing it in your
house or wherever you're doing it. So what do you do? So
you make a hole to collect the blood, but it's a little
bit away from where you're שחטing shecht and then the blood runs
into, right, maybe it's on slanted ground or whatever it is, and
the blood can run into the hole, but don't שחט shecht directly
in the hole.
And so this means it necessarily has to be outside in? You
can't do it on an outside... No, we're going to get... No,
no, we're going to get to outside and in in a minute.
You're right. Inside it's more clear that you're trying to keep your
house clean, but presumably this would apply in your yard as well
because let's look at the next case. Okay. ובשוק לא יעשה כן,
u'bashuk lo ya'aseh ken, in the marketplace where it's not your responsibility
to keep a clean marketplace, right, they didn't believe there in sort
of, clean up your trash, and if it's the marketplace, what do
you care? So there you can't, you cannot do it even if
the hole is a little bit removed because why the heck do
you care about the blood in the marketplace? So if you're making
a hole even if it's a little removed, it still looks like
you're using it, going to use it for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
Oh, so it's not because you don't want people slipping and damaging
themselves? Right, apparently there was an assumption that people wouldn't care if
they had blood splattered in the marketplace. So if you are nevertheless
trying to be a conscientious citizen, okay, it nevertheless, because not every,
most people won't assume that of you, they'll more readily assume that
you're doing it for עבודה זרה avodah zarah, than being a conscientious
citizen, at least it's a possibility. So don't שחט shecht in the
marketplace, just do it on like flat ground? Yeah, in the marketplace
do it on flat ground, but you cannot make a ditch or
a hole, right, you cannot make a hole even a little removed
because people will not say, oh, he's just trying to keep things
clean. Okay. שלא, shelo, and the reason all of these things are
forbidden, this last line really is going on everything, שלא יחקה את
הצדוקים, shelo yechakeh et ha'tzedukim, that you should not copy the, our
גרסא girsa says הצדוקים, ha'tzedukim, Sadducees. I'll talk about that in a
minute. Okay, anyway, in modern Hebrew, the word חיקוי chikui means to
mimic or to copy. רש״י Rashi says that in the משנה Mishna
it's coming from the word חוק, chok, which means a ritual practice.
So you should not do things that are ritual practices of, of
idolatrous. Now why does it call it- why does it say צדוקים?
tzedukim? Right? צדוקים tzedukim were not idolaters, the Sadducees had different interpretations
of תורה שבעל פה, Torah she'ba'al peh, they rejected- they weren't idolaters.
So the point is that that's not the right גרסא. girsa. The
right גרסא girsa in all of the משניות mishnayot is מינים. minim.
Okay, the, now מין min could mean idolaters, it could also mean
Jews that had, like we saw before, אין לך מומר גדול מזה,
ein lecha mumar gadol mizeh, a Jew that had gone over to
become an idolater. Okay, but it was changed again presumably, I imagine,
I don't know the history, but so many things were changed in
the Middle Ages because of self-censorship, and particularly who were the ones
that told the Church about all the bad stuff that made us
now have to go and change? It was the apostates, in other
words, the מינים, minim, the ones that left Judaism for another religion.
Okay, so this is actually something that's referring to, you're a Jew,
but I'm going to suspect you of being an idol- of somebody
who has a Jewish idolater. So you don't want to look like
a Jew that's abandoned Judaism, you don't want to look like a
Jewish idolater, שלא יחקה את המינים, shelo yechakeh et ha'minim, you should
not mimic the מינים, minim, but that was changed due to realities
of the Middle Ages to read צדוקים. tzedukim. Okay, so let's now
go on. Now, by the way, I did want to say one
other quick thing which is, how much is מראית עין marit ayin
a problem of, in general, is a problem that I don't want
people thinking bad things of myself or is it a problem that
I myself don't want to do activities that don't feel kosher even
though technically they are kosher is always a good question. But it's
also a question about whether the משניות, mishnayot, at what degree at
the tannaitic level was there the same degree of concern of appearances
of מראית עין marit ayin as there was in later times at
the in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, it's definitely a phrase that much
more and a concern that much more comes up at the גמרא
Gemara. time than in the משנה Mishnah time. So in terms of
why this is forbidden, שלא יחקה את המינים, shelo yechakeh et ha'minim,
you know, to me that phrase represents an- a little bit different
than מראית עין. Maris Ayin. מראית עין Maris Ayin is more I'm
concerned about other people's perception of what I'm doing, right? שלא יחקה
את המינים shelo yechakeh et haminim means I myself don't want to
do certain actions that are ritual actions of non-Jews. It just doesn't
feel. It's like the position of הרחק מן הכיעור ומן הדומה לו.
Harchik min hachiyur umin hadomeh lo. Keep away from things that are
disgusting and even things that are similar to things that are disgusting.
Don't do the types of activities that feel טרייף treif even if
they're not טרייף. treif. And that's just for my own sense, or
my own religious sensibilities and propriety and so on. So I would
just question to what degree this is really מראית עין Maris Ayin
and concern about other people's perception and whether this is just for
my own type of sense of propriety. Don't do certain types of
things that don't feel כשר. kosher.
Although, again, the distinction between am I doing it at home and
am I doing it in the marketplace might suggest that perception matters.
But nevertheless, how the resonance of an action is different in different
places even for me, not just for others. So I just put
that out there in terms of that question. I will also say
very quickly that it is quite fascinating today when you read some
of within the last fifty years but even more so within the
last ten years, some of the debates that go on around certain
practices in the Orthodox community, particularly ones that are of more egalitarian
nature, inclusive of women, but there are other things as well, that
even if halachically okay, obviously very often the more traditionalists resist because
and one of the reasons, one of the reasons might have to
do with because of basic reasons that more people that are more
traditional resist feminism is because of questions about women's role and so
on, but one of the reasons often stated explicitly is because they
see this as, oh, we're all becoming Conservative Jews. Okay. So and
that reason to reject it and resist it is because it is
a marker of non-Orthodox Judaism in their eyes. So sometimes the phrase
that actually is used in these תשובות tshuvos about these types of
things is that this is forbidden because it is חיקוי המינים chikui
haminim or חיקוי הגוים, chikui hagoyim, because it is mimicking what the
non-Jews do, or mimicking what the apostates do, and by that they
basically mean non-Orthodox Jews, Conservative Jews. So I actually once had somebody
when I do a כתובה kesubah
for a wedding, if the חתן chosson and כלה kallah want, and
nowadays most of the time they do,
the ones that are coming to me at least, want the mother's
name in the כתובה kesubah as well, so it says so-and-so בן
ben father and mother, or בת bas father and mother. So I
once had a rabbi who I'm friendly with and a pretty moderate
guy, and he called me up and he said, I understand that
you include the mother's name in the כתובה. kesubah. I said yes.
He said, could you tell me what your basis is for that?
So I said, I don't think that that's any different than including
the family name, which was not originally in the גמרא, Gemara. but
it gives greater identity. So this also gives greater identity. I'm not
not having the father's name. I don't see what the problem is.
I said, what do you think the problem is?
So he says, I think it's a serious question of חיקוי המינים.
chikui haminim. Oh right, cause Conservative Jews do it. So that is
it. I find that very deeply disturbing.
On the one hand it's refreshing that they're being honest about what
their real concern is,
not הלכה but that
it feels too much like Conservative Judaism. But to take the issue
going on here, which is about idolatry and about certain types of
acts and all of a sudden abstract it and generalize it and
apply it, it's very disturbing, but it actually does come up more
and more frequently around these types of issues. So let's... you're then
prohibiting the permitted. Right. That's what they're doing. They're prohibiting that which
is legally permitted. Right. Yep. Okay. So now let's look at the
גמרא. Gemara Okay. But I couldn't pass that phrase by without telling
you that it really has contemporary import. People are using this phrase
as a way of rejecting permissible things because they feel it feels
like non-Orthodox Judaism. It feels like something that's been adopted by other
denominations. Yes. There's just a lot of murky stuff going on here.
If you look at ritual in the Catholic Church, I've come to
the conclusion that much of their stuff, a huge percentage comes from
Orthodox Jews. It was literally lifted. And you know what? They finally
did it so well that we feel we're copying them, so we
shouldn't do it. With the organs and all the convoluted reasoning. Right.
So it is true. This does open up a huge category of
questions about religious syncretism and borrowing and all those... the חוקות הגויים
chukos hagoyim and all those types of questions. So, tip of the...
iceberg, we don't but moving on. Moving on. Exactly. All right. Can
we get back to עבודה זרה? avodah zarah, All right. Exactly. Okay,
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara We have to really
end on time. I'm actually going to end a little a little
early today because I'm on a schedule. אין שוחטין לא לתוך. Ein
shochtin lo l'toch. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara
מאי שנא לתוך ימים דלא? mai shna l'toch yammim d'lo? Why can't
you do it into an ocean? דאמרי לשרה דימא קא שחיט, d'amri
l'sara d'yamma ka shachit, you're slaughtering to the spirit of the ocean.
לתוך עוגה של מים נמי אמרי לבבואה קא שחיט, l'toch uga shel
mayim nami amri l'babuah ka shachit, even in a puddle of water
you're slaughtering to not the god of the puddles, but slaughtering to
your image, the reflection. Maybe you see that there's a spirit that
is creating your reflection in the water and maybe you're doing it
for that. אמר רבא באחורים שנו. Amar Rava b'achurim shanu. Okay, it's
dirty water, murky water, like Bobby, we're dealing with murky water. Okay,
אין שוחטין לגומא, ein shochtin l'gumah, you don't do it right into
a hole. והא אמרת אין שוחטין לגומא כלל, V'ha amart ein shochtin
l'gumah klal, but it said you can slaughter in your house. So
what does it mean? Said don't slaughter, but you can slaughter in
your house. So didn't we say don't slaughter? אמר אביי רישא בגומא
שבשוק. Amar Abaye reisha b'gumah shebashuk. No, we're talking about don't slaughter
in a hole in the marketplace, in your house you always can
do it. Not the way I read it, I read the conclusion
of the גמרא Gemara. that it runs off into the hole. אמר
ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, רבא Rava said to him, ומי דתני
סיפא, u'mi d'tani seifa, the end of the משנה Mishnah says ובשוק
לא יעשה כן, u'vashuk lo ya'aseh kein, don't do it in the
marketplace regardless. מכלל דרישא לאו בשוק עסקינן, Mikhlal d'reisha lav bashuk askinan,
so the first part of the משנה mishna we weren't even talking
about the marketplace. אלא אמר רבא הכי קאמר. Ela amar Rava hachi
ka'amar. This is what we're saying. אין שוחטין לגומא כל עיקר. Ein
shochtin l'gumah kol ikkar. Don't slaughter directly into a hole regardless, even
in your home. והרוצה לנקר חצרו כיצד הוא עושה? V'harotzeh l'naker chatzero
keitzad hu oseh? If you want to keep your yard clean, what
do you do if you can't slaughter into the hole? עושה מקום
חוץ לגומא ושוחט, Oseh makom chutz l'gumah v'shochet, make a place for
yourself out of the hole, meaning a place that's like slanted and
smooth, that it will run off, slaughter there. והדם שוטת ויורד לגומא
V'hadam shotet v'yored l'gumah and the blood will trickle into the hole.
ובשוק לא יעשה כן U'vashuk lo ya'aseh kein but even that you
cannot do in the marketplace, שלא יחקה את הצדוקים או את המינים,
shelo yechakeh et hatzedukim o et haminim, not to do something that
looks like a ritual of the idolaters. תניא כוותיה דרבא, Tanya k'vateih
d'Rava, we taught like רבא. Rava. היה מהלך בספינה ואין לו מקום
בספינה לשחוט, Haya m'halech b'sfina v'ein lo makom b'sfina lishchot, you're on
a boat and there's no place on the boat to slaughter. Right,
good point. How do you get fresh meat on a boat before
refrigeration? You bring cows with you on the boat and you slaughter
them there, nice fresh meat on the boat. Okay, and you have
no place to slaughter and you don't want to get the boat
bloody. מוציא ידו חוץ לספינה ושוחט, Motzi yado chutz lasfina v'shochet, you
sort of put your hand, meaning the cow's neck, right outside over
the edge of the boat and you can slaughter. והדם שוטת ויורד
על דופני הספינה. V'hadam shotet v'yored al dofnei hasfina. That's okay, that's
slaughtering into the oceans, if you do it just over the edge
so the blood first hits the wall of the boat and then
goes down into the ocean. Since it's not going directly into the
ocean, that's okay. Quick question, if... which one is the one that...
חיה chaya you do כיסוי הדם? kisuy hadam? You do not have
to do כיסוי kisuy here. Right, no, but let's say you did
and but you couldn't do it. I mean then you would have
to bring with you dirt and lay it down and whatever. You
can't just... there's no exceptions? Right, I mean you could not do
the מצוה, mitzvah, but no, if you are obligated to ensure that
you can do it with you know with the dirt and do
it. Okay. Okay. ואין שוחטין לגומא כל עיקר, V'ein shochtin l'gumah kol
ikkar, you can never slaughter directly into a hole. והרוצה לנקר חצרו,
V'harotzeh l'naker chatzero, if you want to keep your field clean, you
do like we did on the boat. כיצד הוא עושה? Keitzad hu
oseh? What do you do? עושה מקום חוץ לגומא ושוחט, Oseh makom
chutz l'gumah v'shochet, you have a place outside of the hole which
is set up, meaning angled and smooth. והדם שוטת ויורד לגומא V'hadam
shotet v'yored l'gumah and the blood runs into the hole. ובשוק לא
יעשה כן, U'vashuk lo ya'aseh kein, don't do this in the marketplace,
משום שנאמר mishum shene'emar because it says ובחוקותיהם u'v'chukoteihem and that's a
certain word of חוק chok in their practices לא תלכו, lo teleichu,
don't go. Now that raises a larger question of what is considered
to be non-Jewish practice, right? Is wearing clothes of you know that's
accepted in secular society non-Jewish practice? But certainly the major major concern
of ובחוקותיהם u'v'chukoteihem is when the practices are sourced in עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. And it's some type of an act that has that
is sourced in עבודה זרה. avodah zarah, So here it's actually saying
more than that, it's saying it's not because it looks to other
people like maybe that's what you're doing, but it actually is a
ritual. But of course it raises serious questions because you know what
makes it... just because my act of slaughtering happens to be the
same actions that a non-Jew would do in their act of עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah you know what makes it a ritual rather than
just the circumstances of my action? You know, if you were to
tell me, for example, you know what's a good example of a
classic ובחוקותיהם? u'v'chukoteihem? Here's an example that gets discussed and I'm not
going to debate this right now, but just to give you an
example that's discussed. Let's say... let's say going trick-or-treating on Halloween. So
you could say, well nowadays that's no longer it's no longer observed
as a as a you know as a pagan type of a
practice, although people could debate that. But even if it's not observed
as that, it has its roots in that and it's a type
of a and it's a type of a custom and a practice
that has its roots. That's fine. But you can't tell me don't
slaughter my cow because pagans slaughter cows when they're making offerings to
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah right? It's not... It's not a ritual, it's
just שחיטה shechting my cow. So I just happen to be שחיטה
shechting my cow in the marketplace, nothing makes it a ritual. So
you could say it looks like a form of עבודה זרה. That
was sort of what the משנה mishna says. But to say it's
forbidden because of בחוקותיהם, bechukoteihem, you have to actually make it some
type of a, you know, you would think you have to make
it some type of a ritual and not that just by circumstance
it parallels something else. But it's a little bit vague because there
are other גמרות gemarot that speak about for example, even when it's
not related to עבודה זרה, that the court doesn't execute, the בית
דין beis din of ישראל doesn't execute in a way that they
execute in non-Jewish courts because of בחוקותיהם. bechukoteihem. So even though you're
motivated for your own reasons, at a certain point when it very
much evokes non-Jewish practice, or particularly non-Jewish idolatrous practice, at what point
does it become בחוקותיהם? bechukoteihem? But this gets to your other question
Bobby and again there's not a clear answer, I'm just throwing out
a lot of questions. Classic תשובות teshuvos that were raised for example
in some in the Middle Ages, can we go to the graveyards
to to pray? I'm not getting to the question about praying to
God and not praying to the to the dead, which is a
different issue of בחוקותיהם, bechukoteihem, but can we do that because that's
also what the non-Jews do? And the basically the רשב"א Rashba says
so are we supposed to stop דאווענען davening because it's what the
non-Jews do? Easy! So anyway so that becomes a question about how
do you identify, you know, what makes it a non-Jewish practice but
also what makes it considered like I'm doing this as a practice
rather than just by circumstance. I happen to be שחיטה shechting in
a marketplace. Quick question and then well let me just read the
last two words: ואם עשה כן v'im asah chein and if the
person did it, צריך בדיקה אחרת. tzarich bedikah acheret. Then you have
to say oh my god this guy's שחיטה shechting in a marketplace
and he's collecting the blood or whatever. We better find out whether
this guy is might be an עובד עבודה זרה. oved avodah zarah.
And if he is, then we have to keep our distance from
him and not eat his wine and drink all these other things.
So you raise serious suspicions about whether you're really, you know, a
good Jew or not if you do these type of practices. Does
that apply today that you have to do בדיקה אחרת? bedikah acheret?
No, all these things are contextual. Yes. The issue on Halloween is
it's a Christian holiday but the practices today are completely different from
what they used to be. Aha. So... Right, to what degree are
these actually the original practices as well? But is it Christian? I
thought the Christians took it over from pagans. Oh yeah it's a
night of, it was also All Saints' Day is November 1st. Yeah
but didn't they conflate it with with a pagan holiday? Well it's
a syncretism but it was originally the night of fasting and prayer
before All Saints' Day. Oh my god. And it was is it
is a Christian holiday that appeared. It is a hallowed evening. Halloween.
That's right. Hallowed evening. Right. Just to say, the thing was it
was originally pagan. Right. Right and then it got everything got mixed.
I got you. Basically that if they didn't sacrifice human beings because
it got dark they'd never see the sun again. That was the
pagan view. Interesting. It then was taken over when the Christians came
in they went over they took over all these pagan holidays and
Christianized. I got you. Bobby I just have one question, how do
you know so much about this? I read. All right. Let's go
on. All right. I just think that's what you asked before about
how the rabbis know about בדיקה אחרת. bedikah acheret. All right exactly.
And now we got to end this. Okay. Okay people I'm I'm
on a clock we got to end this. Last משנה Mishnah. of
the פרק. perek. השוחט לשם עולה לשם זבחים לשם אשם תלוי לשם
פסח לשם תודה. Hashochet l'shem olah l'shem zvachim l'shem asham talui l'shem
pesach l'shem todah. Now it's not עבודה זרה but it is things
that are still look inappropriate because the other inappropriate thing you could
do with שחיטה shechting other than עבודה זרה is bringing a קרבן
korban outside of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay so let's take
a look. השוחט לשם עולה לשם זבחים לשם אשם תלוי לשם פסח
לשם תודה. Hashochet l'shem olah l'shem zvachim l'shem asham talui l'shem pesach
l'shem todah. שחיטתו פסולה. shechitah-to pesulah. If you שחט shecht for any
of these קרבנות korbanot meaning it's not a קרבן, korban your animal
is not a קרבן, korban, but as you're שחיטה shechting it you're
saying I am שחיטה shechting this so it should be an עולה.
olah. I am שחיטה shechting this so it should be a שלמים.
shlamim. It's not, it's a חולין chulin but you're sort of trying
to say that's the type of שחיטה shechitah you're doing. So in
all those cases it's not really קדשים בחוץ kodshim bachutz because it's
not really a קודש, kodesh, you haven't sanctified it, but it's invalid
because... He's saying saying עולה olah is not sanctifying it? No. No.
If you actually sanctify it, הרי זו עולה, harei zo olah, right.
Okay but anyway this is not קדשים בחוץ kodshim bachutz but it
looks like it. So again it's a problem of what it looks
like and because it looks like it שחיטתו פסולה shechitah-to pesulah the
שחיטה shechitah is invalid. רבי שמעון מכשיר. Rebbi Shimon machshir. רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon says it's okay. Why? רש"י Rashi says רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon is not so concerned about appearances. תוספות Tosfos says because רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon would say as we have in another גמרא Gemara
that wait a minute because רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon would say that
you know that it doesn't even that the animal is not actually...
let me just find the words of the גמרא Gemara second... yes
that it doesn't even look like a קרבן korban. because if you're
sanctifying something to be brought outside of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
which is what it does look like, then according to רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon the animal never becomes sanctified. If you say הרי זו
עולה harei zo olah that I should bring it outside the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it has no קדושה. kedushah. Okay because you're trying
to reframe what its status is as an עולה. olah. So רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon says... so... no... קדשים בחוץ kodshim bachutz is you
said הרי זו עולה harei zo olah and you closed your mouth
or you even intended at the time to bring it in the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and then you brought it outside. But if
you actually say הרי זו עולה על מנת שאביאנה חוץ לבית המקדש,
harei zo olah al m'nat she'avienah chutz l'Beis HaMikdash, according to רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon it's not even an עולה. olah. So רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon is it doesn't even look like it because you know
even if you were to really try to make it an עולה
olah it wouldn't... No, you just said I'm שוחט shochting this לשם
עולה, l'shem olah, but he says it can't be worse than saying
הרי זה עולה לשם harei zeh olah l'shem whatever, and it doesn't
even look like sacrifice outside because according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
it would not even be binding. Since we have before? No, because
you said according to one of the appearances. Oh, according to רש״י.
Rashi. Yeah, that's a question according to רש״י Rashi why he didn't
debate the previous משנה. Mishnah Okay, we have, I'm sorry Michael just
no more questions. שנים אוחזין בסכין ושוחטין, Shenayim ochzin b'sakin v'shochtin, again
two people holding the knife, אחד לשום אחד מאלו, echad l'shum echad
m'eilu, one for one of these things, sort of קרבנות korbanos slot,
ואחד לשום דבר כשר, v'echad l'shum davar kasher, and one for a
non-קרבן korban, slot, so similar to before except here it's about a
קרבן, korban. שחיטתו פסולה, shechitatos pesulah, it's invalid. Again, because it still
looks wrong. השוחט לשם חטאת לשם אשם ודאי לשם בכור לשם מעשר
לשם תמורה, Hashocheit l'shem chatas l'shem asham vadai l'shem bechor l'shem ma'aser
l'shem tmurah, if you'd slaughter for any of these קרבנות korbanos which
are not קרבנות korbanos that you can freely create. These are only
קרבנות korbanos that are obligatory. חטאת, Chatas, a sin offering. אשם ודאי,
Asham vadai, an אשם asham which is another type of a sin
sacrifice. בכור, Bechor, firstborn. You know, it would have to really be
a בכור, bechor, okay and presumably it's not. Okay or, or מעשר,
ma'aser, yes you do designate every tenth animal of the newborn, but
if you have not yet designated it, you can't designate one animal
you have standing here as the tenth of your flock. It has
to be through a process of counting the flock. So in all
of these cases, even if you were really sanctifying it, it would
not be binding, okay, because you have to do it because it's
only under certain circumstances. Or תמורה, tmurah, an exchange, שחיטתו כשרה, shechitatos
k'sheirah, there it's כשר kosher because even if you were really doing
it, you wouldn't have made it a קרבן. korban. זה הכלל, Ze
hachlal, this is the principle: כל דבר שנידר ונידב, kol davar shenidar
v'nidav, anything that is made through a vow, a free will קרבן,
korban השוחט לשמו אסור, hashocheit l'shmo assur, if you're שוחט shochting for
that purpose it's forbidden because it looks like you made this thing
a קרבן. korban ושאינו נידר ונידב, v'she'eino nidar v'nidav, if it cannot
be done through a free will vow, it's only because of an
obligation like a חטאת, chatas, an אשם, asham, בכור, bechor, it's only...
okay we're going to get to the problems of the משנה Mishnah.
in a minute. Or it's only because of things that are special
circumstances like מעשר ma'aser and so or בכור. bechor. In those cases,
השוחט לשמו כשר, hashocheit l'shmo kasher, it is valid. Okay, so let's
take a look because nobody, it doesn't look like you're doing anything,
it looks like you're crazy, but it doesn't look like you're doing
anything prohibited. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara
השוחט לשם עולה, Hashocheit l'shem olah, so, so it quotes the beginning
of the משנה. Mishnah אשם תלוי Asham talui בר נידר ונידב הוא?
bar nidar v'nidav hu? As Michael said, in the first case of
the משנה that things that were problematic, one of the thing was
an אשם תלוי. asham talui. An אשם תלוי asham talui is a
sin offering I bring when I'm not sure if I sinned. When
I ate something let's say forbidden fat, might have been forbidden fat,
but it might have been כשר. kosher. So I don't know, so
I bring this sin offering to protect me until I can find
out more you know, you know more clearly whether I've sinned or
not. So the גמרא Gemara says that also requires special circumstances, it's
also an obligation, it's not free will. So how come that's a
problem, that looks like I'm really doing it? אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rabbi Yochanan, היי מני רבי אליעזר היא? Hai mani Rabbi Eliezer hi?
This is רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, דאמר מתנדב אדם אשם תלוי בכל
יום. d'amar misnadeiv adam asham talui b'chol yom. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
had this wonderful view of human nature, or maybe, maybe at the
same, maybe he actually did have, maybe he had an honest view
of human nature but he actually wanted to help us, save us
from that. So he said you can every single day bring an
אשם תלוי. asham talui. Because every day you have to be concerned
that maybe you sinned and you don't know about it. Now a
classic אשם תלוי asham talui is you did something concretely and there's
a concrete reason to think you sinned. You ate a piece of
food and somebody says you realize you know that that might have
been חלב, cheilev, okay, or even in a more interesting case there
were two pieces in front of you, one was forbidden fat, one
was כשר kosher fat, and you ate one of them and you
don't know which one. But according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, excuse
me, even just an abstract concern that I might have sinned is
enough of a basis to bring in אשם תלוי asham talui and
therefore he says if you want to bring it every single day,
more power to you. So therefore according to him, I could really
be making this an אשם תלוי asham talui and therefore it looks
bad when I'm doing that and therefore the שחיטה shechita is invalid.
And when do I have so much depression? Yeah, talk about Jewish
guilt. Okay, okay. פסח, Pesach, so now the גמרא Gemara says how
about פסח? Pesach? בר נידר ונידב הוא? Bar nidar v'nidav hu? Why
is פסח Pesach listed? You can't just סתם stam give a פסח
Pesach any time during the year. So זמנו קביע ליה. Zmano kavia
lei. It can only be given in a certain time of the
year, so why are we concerned about if you're saying it you're
doing it for a פסח? Pesach? אמר רבי יהושע, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua,
שאני פסח הואיל ופשוטו כל השנה כולה. shani pesach ho'il v'pashuto kol
hashanah kulah. You don't only give it once in the year, but
you can be set, you can sanctify something for a פסח Pesach
six months earlier. So therefore maybe I am sanctifying it for פסח
Pesach and now I'm שוחט shochting a פסח Pesach before its time
which would still be a שלמים. shlamim. Okay, so yes, it could
actually work. If I really sanctified this as a פסח Pesach even
though right now it's ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and I שוחט shochted
it, it would still be שוחט shochting a, it would still if
I did it in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash it would be
a שלמים. shlamim. So out of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash it
would look, it would be קדשים בחוץ. kodshim bachutz. So yes, it
can still look like a problem by a פסח. Pesach. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבי ינאי, Amar Rabbi Yannai, לא שנו
אלא תמימים. lo shanu ela tmimim. The whole problem of appearances here
is only if the animals are תמימים. tmimim. אבל בעלי מומים, Aval
ba'alei mumim, if they're blemished, מידי ידיע, midi yedi'a, it's, you can
see the blemish. So you know that whatever the guy is saying
it's absurd, it's not a קרבן. korban So, רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi
Yochanan amar, אפילו בעלי מומים נמי, afilu ba'alei mumim nami, even blemished.
זימנין דרמי ליה מידי אמומא, Zimnin deramei lei midi amuma, sometimes something
is covering up the blemish, particularly like wool if it's a sheep,
ולא ידיעא, velo yedia, and it's not known. So if it's missing
a leg then right, well maybe, right. Okay. Or the other, okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara goes on, or you know the other
thing that I don't get what the גמרא Gemara didn't ask is
why didn't somebody say, oh I know what happened, he sanctified it,
it got a מום, mum, and therefore rather than bring it in
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, he's leaving it outside the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. So maybe there's even more reason to suspect it's קדשים
בחוץ, Kodshim Bachutz, you know, because of the מום. mum. That's why
you're not bringing it in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. All right,
I don't know. השוחט לשם חטאת, Hashocheit l'shem Chatas, if you're bringing
it for חטאת. Chatas. אמר רבי יוחנן לא שנו אלא שאינו מחויב
חטאת. Amar Rabi Yochanan lo shanu ela sheino mekhuyav Chatas. When is
it that saying that you're doing it for a חטאת Chatas does
not invalidate? If we don't know that you're obligated in a חטאת.
Chatas. אבל מחויב חטאת, Aval mekhuyav Chatas, if we know you're obligated
in a חטאת, Chatas, we know that you ate חמץ Chometz on
פסח Pesach or something like that by accident. You know, you weren't
told or whatever, okay, it was an innocent mistake, we don't blame
you, but you're חייב חטאת. chayav Chatas. So now you're saying I'm
doing this for a חטאת, Chatas, now it's a problem, because then
it really does look like you're bringing a חטאת Chatas because you're
obligated in one. Okay, so that would be a problem. והא לא
קאמר לשם חטאתי, Veha lo kaamar l'shem Chatosi, one minute, even that
shouldn't be a problem, because when you're slaughtering it you're not saying
for my חטאת. Chatas. When you're just saying, I am bringing this,
I am slaughtering this for the sake of a חטאת, Chatas, that
sort of means like generic חטאת. Chatas. Like I'm just making it
a חטאת Chatas now and it doesn't even relate to any particular
obligation. So the גמרא Gemara says, even if you're חייב chayav in
a חטאת, Chatas, just saying it for the generic sake of a
חטאת Chatas would not make us think that you're actually have sanctified
this to function for your sin and for your חטאת. Chatas. So
the גמרא says, okay, אמר רבא באומר לשם חטאתי, Amar Rava b'omer
l'shem Chatosi, if you said that. So even though if you said
for חטאת Chatas it's not a problem, if you're חייב חטאת, chayav
Chatas, if you've sinned and you're חייב חטאת chayav Chatas and when
you שחט shacht it you're saying for the sake of my חטאת,
Chatas, then it looks like you're actually bringing a חטאת Chatas outside
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and it is a problem. לשם תמורה,
L'shem Tmurah, for תמורה Tmurah it's not a problem. אמר רבי אלעזר
לא שנו אלא שאין לו זבח בתוך ביתו. Amar Rabi Elazar lo
shanu ela shein lo zevach betoch beiso. Similarly, when do we say
it's not a concern if you say it's an exchange, a תמורה,
Tmurah, if you don't have a קרבן korban in your house? אבל
יש לו זבח בתוך ביתו, Aval yesh lo zevach betoch beiso, if
you have a קרבן korban in your house, so אימא תמורי תמיר
ביה, eima tmurei tamir bei, maybe you are doing תמורה, Tmurah, maybe
you maybe you actually do mean it. So the גמרא says, והא
לא קאמר לשם תמורת זבחי, veha lo kaamar l'shem Tmuras zivchi, same
problem, you're just saying generic תמורה, Tmurah, so even if you have
a קרבן korban in your house this would not make it a
תמורה Tmurah of that קרבן korban. if you didn't say it's a
תמורה Tmurah for the קרבן in my house. So the same answer,
אמר רבא באומר לשם תמורת זבחי, Amar Rava b'omer l'shem Tmuras zivchi,
you say you're doing it for the sake of the תמורה Tmurah
in your house. So again, even though you're not really doing it,
but if you have an animal in your house and a קרבן
in your house and you said I am שוחט shochting this for
the sake of the תמורה Tmurah of that thing, then it looks
like קדשים בחוץ. Kodshim Bachutz. You didn't really sanctify it, it's not
really קדשים בחוץ, Kodshim Bachutz, but then it really does look like
that. Okay. זה הכלל, Zeh Haklal, this is the principle, לאתויי מאי,
laasuyei mai, what does this include? לאתויי עולת נזיר, Laasuyei Olas Nazir,
that if you're bringing if you're saying this is לשם עולת נזיר,
l'shem Olas Nazir, that's a problem even though you're not a נזיר.
Nazir. So why doesn't that look absurd? So מהו דתימא mahu d'teima
I might have thought הלו נדר, halo nadar, he never made a
vow to be a נזיר, Nazir, and therefore everybody will realize that
it's absurd. No, people will say maybe you are a נזיר, Nazir,
we just don't know about it. Even if you come down with
your new haircut. Well, right, anyways, if you שחט shacht it for
the sake of an עולה Olah of a נזיר, Nazir, it's a
problem because people might still think you're a נזיר. Nazir. ושאינו נידר
ונידב לאתויי, Vesheino nidar venidav laasuyei, and something that's not normally vowed,
what's that include? לאתויי עולת יולדת. Laasuyei Olas Yoledes. If you say
I'm bringing this as an עולה Olah for my wife who gave
birth. Now why not, maybe your wife did give birth? So let's
take a look. We'll first assume maybe you don't have a wife.
Okay, so then it's not a problem. So אמר רבי אלעזר לא
שנו אלא שאין לו אשה. Amar Rabi Elazar lo shanu ela shein
lo isha. There you go, if you don't have a wife then
nobody's saying you're doing it for the sake of your newly born
child, that's not a problem. אבל יש לו אשה, Aval yesh lo
isha, if you have a wife, אימא לשמה קא עביד, eima l'shmah
ka avid, maybe you're doing it for your wife. So the גמרא
says, והא לא קאמר לשם עולת אשתי. veha lo kaamar l'shem Olas
ishti. No, even that would not be a problem again because you
have not designated it specifically. So you're just generically bringing it as
an עולת יולדת, Olas Yoledes, which even if you just had a
child would not be meaningful. So אמר רבא באומר לשם עולת אשתי.
Amar Rava b'omer l'shem Olas ishti. Oh, if you said it. So
if you have a wife and you're saying I'm doing it for
my wife for the עולה Olah for my wife's childbirth, you know
even if you didn't sanctify it then it does look like you're
trying to sanctify and trying to bring it and it is a
problem. Even if she's like eighty years old? So let's take a
look. פשיטא, Pshita, obviously. מהו דתימא Mahu d'teima I might have thought
אם איתא דילדה קלא הוי ליה, im isah dyaldah kala havei lei,
I would say no if his wife had given birth we would
have heard about it. So maybe even if you say you're doing
it for your wife it's not a problem because everybody knows it's
absurd, everybody knows she hasn't been giving birth. קא משמע לן, Ka
mashma lan, so it comes to teach us איפולי אפיל, ippulai appil,
very sad way to end this פרק, perek, maybe she miscarried, right,
so even if... אימא איפולי אפיל, eima ipulei apil, very sad way
to end this פרק, perek, maybe she miscarried, right? So even if
a woman miscarries, you have to bring an עולת יולדת, olat yoledet,
she's still an עולת יולדת, olat yoledet, maybe not. So therefore we're
concerned, and therefore don't do it, and if you do it, it's
invalid because it looks like you brought a קרבן. חזק חזק ונתחזק.
chazak chazak v'nitchazek. We finished the fourth פרק perek of מסכת זבחים.
masechet zevachim. הדרן עלך בית שמאי hadran alach beit shammai and we
will continue tomorrow, בעזרת השם, b'ezrat hashem, with the next פרק perek
of מסכת זבחים, masechet zevachim, which is the fifth פרק, perek, איזהו
מקומן. eizehu mekomon. Have a wonderful day.